[Music]
Good evening everyone. Welcome to the
December 15th finance committee meeting.
The last one of the year and this term.
should be short and sweet here with just
a few cleanup pieces that we need to do
and introduce. Starting with temporary
resolution 11325
coming through code enforcement and
zoning with Mr. Sullie.
>> Thank you, Corey. Um this is uh for some
plumbing work that had to be done. So um
I'm going to have Chasine come up uh and
tell us just real quick what it was for.
>> Hi, good evening. Um yeah, we had a new
sink installed and some plumbing work
done. Um our the PO was opened up when
we got the invoice instead of um so this
was after the work was done. It created
a then and now situation
>> and there's money in the budget for it
too. So
>> yeah and it's in our budget so we're not
>> okay. It's just for mine with state
state audit you have to have the
purchase order engaged before the
service. So that was just kind of got
the cart before the horse. So be in
order for me to pay the invoice. I need
council's permission to do so.
>> Okay.
>> So we're going to suspend
>> ask for suspension. Mr. Luxembourg is
your second.
>> Yes. Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks Chaz.
Uh ordinances. We have two uh temporary
ordinance 7525
through finance. Um that is a request to
amend two different pay ordinances that
we already approved or I'm sorry that's
the one pay ordinance but it's police
and fire. Uh Mr. Mayor, did you want to
touch on that one?
>> Sure. the uh the original pay ordinance
that we passed was actually the previous
version of that prior to the corrections
being made. The correct version was
emailed to everyone but not included in
the packet that was delivered to you. So
it was just an error of getting that the
information was given to you but it
wasn't brought in front of you here at
the the table. So this is correcting an
error in those salary calculations
uh for police and fire chief. And then
the second ordinance 7625
is municipal court uh had some changes
in their ordinance uh pay ordinance
regarding um the changing a position to
office manager versus uh admin
assistant.
And then um also eliminating the
utilities customer service manager,
which as you know, we eliminated that
position entirely and moved that
individual uh position over to uh
zoning.
So they really are just a cleanup piece.
Again, all this information was emailed
to council. You should have had it to
review. It just didn't get to the formal
legislation, and this needs to be
replaced to make sure we correct those
errors.
Thank you. Any questions?
>> No. Great. So, we're going to ask for
suspension on those. And Mr. Als is my
second. Yes.
>> Great. That's all I have. Uh, department
updates. Do we have anyone here with
department updates? Mr.
Deetsz.
>> Good evening, council. First of all, I'd
like to um start off by thanking the
outgoing members for all the support
you've had for LDOT throughout this year
and years past. And um wish you luck in
your next endeavors. And for any
newcomers that are coming on board, feel
free to come down and see what we do. If
you're around this weekend, you'll see
one of the things we do do that is snow.
Um Saturday, if you're around, it starts
snowing about noon, about 1:00 in the
afternoon, and didn't stop. until
midnight that night. And uh our crews
were in from 11:00 a.m. Saturday till
midnight last night. So 37 hours worth
of being in trucks. Um
we spent a total of uh 67,45.72.
Um the labor we had $42 man hours
involved in all that. That cost us about
$24,000.
And our materials was between 282 tons
of salt and 800 or 8,460 gallons of
brine which we used to pre-treat and uh
wet our solace that comes out of the
trucks. That was another $23,0005
$23,532
worth of materials. So,
um, for anybody who didn't see a truck
out, our trucks averaged, uh, 365 mi a
piece. That's, uh, 10 trucks on the
road. So, if you, uh, weren't where our
trucks were, trust me, they were out.
So, um, if you got any more questions or
have concerns about what we did,
>> how many of the small How many of the
small trucks do you have? We have two
one- ton trucks and we actually wound up
we borrowed the cemetery smaller truck.
It's a it's not quite as long because uh
we've been asked to plow the city lot
behind the courthouse and the PD lot and
it's a little easier to get in and out
with. So,
>> because you had a small truck I saw
small truck out last night that uh it
was good in the in the residential
neighborhood. That was our cemetery
truck which which
>> is very good for the narrow oneway
streets.
>> We do use that. We've got about 50 miles
worth of
>> um 59 miles worth of alleys and oneways
that we can't get a big truck in. So, we
got to use our little truck. So,
um other than that, just want to thank
everybody for their support and we'll go
from there.
>> Perfect. Thank you. Any other questions
from Mr. Deetsz?
All right. Thank you.
>> If you got snow in front of your
driveway, we will get to it. Right now,
the our issue is temperatures. Um snow
is only good or salt is only good down
to about 15 degrees and it hasn't been
much above 15 for the last 24 hours. So,
uh next few days are supposed to get up
in the 50s. So, by midweek hopefully
everything's gone and we'll get ready
for the next one. All right.
Anyone else with department updates?
No. Uh, next thing I have is council
meeting prep. President Porter.
>> Um, yeah. Did you want to use this
opportunity to talk about temporary
ordinance 7425 star?
>> Well, I realize that I put it in your
section versus other discussion items.
That's
>> okay.
>> If you have something,
>> I don't have anything. Okay,
>> we can just move to that.
>> So, temporary ordinance 7425 star if we
want to discuss it because otherwise we
have 23 minutes to sit around and wait
for the regular meeting. So, there's a
star version. You guys saw it after
some conversations looking through the
original.
I I don't I don't know where everybody
is. So, I I had a couple calls. I think
President Porter had a couple calls. If
we want to discuss it before we
get to the regular meeting, I guess this
would be the time if anyone has any
additional thoughts, questions.
Obviously, we can't change it right now,
but we can introduce the star version if
the star version makes more sense than
the original version, or we don't have
to introduce the star version.
Or we can have questions on what happens
if we vote no on it. What happens next?
>> Uh, Mr. Chair, I I'll ask that question.
What happens if we vote no? What What
happens next?
>> I mean, if we vote no, it just stays the
same. We We roll in with
nine committees for next year with 10
people. It can stay the same
or we can look at
one of these other options. We can vote
no. So if we vote no, it stays the same
and then we can discuss at the reorg
meeting which is when was that scheduled
for? I'm sorry I don't have
>> the 5th. So we can discuss it but then
we're in a situation where we have a new
piece of legislation.
It's not voted one
>> that well then everything's what council
the whole the first meeting we could
vote to pass some new piece of
legislation.
It's just
>> and just and be clear Mr. Chair we vote
no that means all the other rules as
well that are being proposed also go
away. Just right
>> once again saying that for the sake of
clarity.
>> Right.
>> All right.
>> We can pass it. We can roll with this.
We could pass this and then turn around
at the reorg meetings, someone comes up
with something different
>> and then consider a new piece of
legislation with a new idea and then we
end up voting on it at some, you know,
at the first meeting.
>> Do we have the option to table it and
then
>> No, because you're changing terms and
there will be new people. It it has to
be either passed or denied tonight.
Sorry.
>> Got it. Thank you.
>> Yeah. I'm I'm not opposed to change.
Lived my whole life. Things change. You
can't do anything about it. But I don't
understand the reason for this change. I
haven't heard a good explanation as to
why we're changing it. We had
you didn't have a committee. You didn't
chair a committee this year.
>> Mhm. and it worked out fine. Right. I I
feel that every person that's elected to
the Langster City Council ought to have
the opportunity to chair a committee,
not co-chair a committee.
I don't care what anyone says. The vice
chair is the vice chair, not the chair.
>> And it makes a difference.
And
you know, I I recall
when I when I ran before in 1980, there
were five brand new council people.
And guess what? We each chaired a
committee. We were all under 30 years
old, didn't know anything, thought we
knew everything.
And
the institution survived.
We survived. the city of Lancaster
thrived and prospered. People either
jump in and figure it out
or they get exposed.
That's how it works. That's always how
it's how it's worked. And I propose that
we not change anything. Thank you.
I agree with everything he said, but in
1980 I was 17 and not on council.
>> And he wasn't born yet.
>> Most of them probably were.
>> And
>> Mr. Lux,
>> I'm with Larry. I agree with everything
you said. Keep it at keep it at 10.
>> Mr. Wing, I just want to make a quick
comment here about the STAR version.
>> Um, I do appreciate the work that's gone
into this. My one concern with the star
version is if I remember correctly, it
uh puts storm water and environmental
engineering in a different committee
than water and water pollution control.
>> And my concern with that is all those
departments work so closely together. I
think they should be in the same
committee.
>> Okay.
I guess I I'll ask the question uh here
on the floor, but you know, hearing
feedback from these other council, you
know, from the other members of council
here around the table, could we amend
from the floor?
>> Ask Stephanie, on that one.
>> Not not to make your life more
difficult, Law Director Hall, but I I'm
just listening to folks here.
>> Yeah. Um
typically the legislation is given to
the clerk in writing before the meeting
starts and that way um the clerk of
council has it has the ability to you
know share that with the public for the
purposes of public records and
transparency.
>> Um there's nothing in the rules that
precludes you from doing that. Um I just
want to be you know super careful about
how you did it to make sure that you
know everything was clear to everybody.
Um, and that might that might take a
written motion that, you know, separates
all of the different departments out.
Um, if you're going to do the the five
instead of the nine that we currently
have.
>> Um, but
>> you can do it technically. Yes,
>> I appreciate that. Thank you.
>> Yep.
>> It would be an easy switch. I mean, it's
just one
one section, one article.
111.06.01.
101. We could strike that from it and
pass pass everything else
cuz I'm fine with the rest of it. I
don't know that. Does anybody object to
anything else
in it?
>> Mr. Ring,
>> I just wanted to clarify. I didn't want
my comments to be misconstrued. I say
generally I think we should have nine or
10 committees.
>> Okay.
Yes,
>> I guess being represent being
representative of one of the new members
of council and not being on a committee
at the moment. Um, for the record, I'm
not shying away from chairing a
committee. So, that's if that's if we
haven't really determined what the
reasoning is the reasoning to ease
people into this, um, I don't feel it's
necessary.
I so we go ahead because
>> I wanted to provide a little
>> you ran you ran the law committee
meeting. I think it we got an email from
law director hall this afternoon that
kind of explained how we got to that
idea but please go ahead.
>> Yeah. So the committee right at first
was considering should we move from nine
to 10 committees because we have 10
council people and the question was
raised should we challenge ourselves to
reduce the number of committees and part
of the reason why it helps alleviate the
burden and obligation on our
administration. Some of our
administrative um
leaders um are required or at least
expected to go to the majority if not
all of these committee meetings. That's
a lot of meetings for them and it takes
a lot of time out of their day. Also,
it's more collaboration with individual
council members. Having more individual
members on, you know, fewer fewer number
of committees helps people be part of
the process up front. You're part of the
discussion. You're part of the question
and answer session in those committees.
You can get your concerns addressed
sooner in the process. Be able to
educate your constituents along the way
and have a little more buy into the
process. Having a chair and vice chair
creates collaboration, helps spread the
duties and responsibilities and it
doesn't, you know, remove the chair and
vice chair's ability to, you know,
create and approach the operational
execution of that committee in any
specific way. You have control over
that. And then I've heard concerns not
only from current council members, but
also future council members who are
already elected. And I guess I would
just ask, you know, we have 33 state
senators, 18 committees. Are the 15 that
don't have those chair um, you know,
positions, are they hampered or, you
know, representing their constituents
any less just because they don't have
that chairmanship, chairpersonship?
That would be all that I would ask. And
it's not that we are trying to create
change. It's we're trying to think
outside the box and what's the best
approach going forward. And it doesn't
always mean it's the status quo or what
we've always done.
>> Very well said. Yeah. Yes.
The reality of the fact of having a
number of committees is based upon
operational need. So we should be
addressing subject matter in committees
that is pertinent and is relevant to the
group of people who are assembled. those
members of the administration as council
member Kitz u alluded to on the back end
of this and I think we tried to do this
at the beginning of our last council
term and there was some push back and I
would challenge all new council members
and existing council members to look at
making sure other council members are
aware of the work that's going on. One
of the ways that I proposed at the
beginning of last term was that we
utilize a uniform looking minutes
document that we can all use that it
looks the same that people can read
including our constituents and have them
read that and know this is what a
minutes document looks like. this is the
work that's going on in this committee.
And also challenge ourselves to get
those minutes done in a timely fashion
after that committee meeting so all of
their fellow council members whether or
not they could attend or or not could
could actually read that information and
digest it before the legislation gets to
them um in our regular meeting. So
regardless of the number of council u
committees that we have whether it be
nine 10 five we should be going for the
goal of making sure there's a lot of
transparency in what's going on and
education of uh us and our fellow
members if in fact there's information
that we should be getting from those
committees.
Miss Tener.
>> Um, another thing is like our water
meetings. How long do they last
sometimes, Michael? One and a half, two
hours. And then if you have these, are
people going to be able to get off work
for three? I mean, I know a lot of
times, Christine, you had that you had
work. So, you know, I mean,
>> it's could be three or four hours out of
your day. Is your job going to let you
do that? I mean, that's one reason why
we would have them early in the morning
and they would be
>> Yeah.
>> You know,
>> I think so. So there's merit to
everybody in the conversation, which is
why we opened it up the way that we did.
You know, I think so to to Becky's
point,
it it's then it turns into a working
together on the logistics of it. So some
of these are bigger. There's a lot more
to digest, but you have some committees
that meet every other month or only once
a quarter. This setup almost kind of
forces the issue like meat once a month,
but then you can look at it as hey maybe
you okay so let's use utilities with
water right so water does a lot of stuff
you might need to have your
superintendent at every monthly meeting
you might have superintendent on your
committee that don't need to be there
every month unless for some reason they
have something that comes up so I mean
again kind of continuing to think
outside the box. You don't you know
maybe it's a maybe it's one of those
things monthly with safety that it's
police is the focus of that particular
month fire is the next month and then if
something comes up I think it's one of
those things we're trying to also think
of so you're not having so much like we
I've been on committees where we only
met once a quarter but then just how
this calendar fell we would be doing
more business through email than
actually
on you know during committee meetings.
So, it was kind of one of those things,
too. How do you how do you get more
people in the room when you're making
those decisions? So, everybody, again,
I've said I'm not married to any one of
them, will figure it out. We are,
contrary to popular belief, sometimes
we're grown adults. We can figure it
out. At the same time, does this make it
more efficient? Does this make everybody
a little more accountable by the fact
that you are in more of the discussion?
You're not just like bringing back
parks, like we got rid of parks because
we didn't really have any say in a parks
meeting. So, you know, bringing it back
just to say we had a 10th one didn't
really quite make sense to us when we
were sitting in and having that
discussion. Keeping it the same is fine,
but then we roll into the should should
everyone be a little more involved with
that? So, I didn't have a problem
sitting with no chair um because I knew
as a prom if I was going to have to do
those meetings or if if Bob at the time
couldn't be there that I'd be able to
fill in. So, it didn't it didn't bother
me doing that way. And that's the first
time we had done it that way. I think
this term was the first time that a
council member didn't have a chair and
it worked out fine for that purpose. Is
it going to work out fine the next time?
Maybe not. So, it's something to
consider. And I'd like to also point out
like we we can change it if we realize
that okay, we made a mistake. We can fix
it. We can change it anytime we want.
That's that's the other food for
thought. So, if you don't like it how
how we presented it, I'll present the
star version or I'm sorry, Christine is
going to present the star version. And
then if if you'd rather stick with how
it is now or you want to see something
different, then just vote no. And then
Then we'll go from there. We'll pivot
and we'll figure it out.
I'm off my soap box. You weren't okay.
Discussion. Any more discussion on that
one? Any other discussion for finance?
Seeing none, I'll ask for a motion to
adjurnn.
>> So moved. Second,
>> Mr. Hails.
>> Second by Mr. Sully. It's 6:23 and we
are adjourned.
Uh, the regular session of Lancaster
City Council will begin promptly at
6:30.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 74-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
>> Hi, I'm Stephanie Taylor with Habitat
for Humanity of Southeast Ohio. We
believe everyone deserves a safe,
healthy, and affordable place to call
home. and we provide home ownership and
repairs for families in need. This
month, we are proud to be chosen by the
Buckeye family's Buckeye Cares program.
They'll make a generous donation with
each car sold. Whether it's having
employees help out on job sites or
supporting us financially, we say thanks
Buckeye for your ongoing support.
[Music]
Grant us the serenity to accept the
things that we cannot change, the
courage to change the things we can, and
finally, the wisdom to know the
difference. I now call the December 15th
Lancaster City Council meeting to order.
Please join me in the pledge of
allegiance. I pledge algiance to the
flag of the United States of America and
to the republic for which it stands. One
nation under God, indivisible, with
liberty and justice for all.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als here.
>> Mr. Bisjack here.
>> Mr. Carr
>> here.
>> Mrs. K here.
>> Mrs. Hoop here.
>> Mr. Luxembourg
>> here.
>> Mr. Mr. Skunover
>> here,
>> Mr. Sullie
>> Miss Tiner
>> here,
>> and Mr. W
>> here. Please let the record reflect that
all 10 members of Lancaster City Council
are present.
>> Reading and disposing of the journal.
>> Excuse me. I have regular meeting
minutes dated December 1st, 2025.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and file the journal. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. All those post same sign. Reports of
city officials.
>> I have six of them. I have email dated
December 1st, 2025 regarding Taylor real
estate tiff submitted by law director
Hall. Email dated December 1st, 2025
regarding city of Lancaster CRA3
amendment submitted by law law director
Stephanie Hall. Email data December 3rd,
2025. Um, November of 2025. Income tax
collection report submitted by tax
commissioner Amy Hamilton. Email dated
December 4th, 2025. Service committee
meeting cancelled submitted by council
member Larry Als. Email dated December
8th, 2025 regarding Elmwood Park
playground submitted by parks assistant
superintendent Jennifer Shamblin. An
email dated December 9th, 2025. Water
regarding water water pollution
committee. I apologize. I have nine of
them. Meeting cancellization submitted
by council member Michael Wing. Email
dated December 10th, 2025 regarding Port
Authority Board reappoint submitted by
Mayor Don McDaniel. Email dated December
13, 2025 regarding winter lights
cancellization submitted by park
superintendent Steve Gayfield. And the
last one is series of emails dated
December 15th regarding law committee
council rules submitted by council
president Jeff Porter and law director
Stephanie Hall.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and file the reports of city officials.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Now move
on to communications.
>> I have three. I have email dated
December 1st, excuse me, 2025 regarding
Taylor real estate tiff submitted by
Darber Douly with Bricker Graden. series
of emails dated December 5th through the
9th Dece or 2025 regarding Casto plans
submitted by Zachary Gerald with
Columbus business first law director
Stephanie Hall and city planner Chelen
Carter series of emails dated December
2nd 2025 um regarding city of Lancaster
PACE a PACE
um-20
through 203 South Broad Street submitted
by Derby Douly with Brooker Bricker
Braden and law director Stephanie Hall.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communications.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and second receive and
file the communications. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Special
presentations and awards. There are um
>> no, we'll do we'll do them in new
business.
>> We have none.
>> Thank you. Uh petitions and memorials.
There are no petitions or memorials this
evening.
>> We have now reached the time for
permission of voters and taxpayers to
address city council. Are there any
individuals here this evening who wish
Okay, sir. It Let me give you the rules.
If you approach the podium, you need to
put your name and address on to
>> I'm good.
>> Okay. And it's a threem minute limit.
>> I want to be done in three minutes.
>> Okay. Thank you. Just giving you the
rules. Thank you. Um, my name is
Terrence Fe. Live at 11 195 Cincinnati
Zanesville Road, Lancaster. Want my
number? I'll give it to you. 7402700937.
The mayor knows who I am. Stephanie
knows exactly who I am.
Um, I'm here to ask the mayor and the
council
and I have a live recording
of Stephanie on the telephone with me.
Um, I've been to
the state house because of her actions.
I've talked to a council uh a
congressman and a senator to remove her
from the law director's office
because of her attitude, her dismember.
I'm the you guys.
>> Sir, sir, I know I'm just you you do not
address the audience. You don't address
anybody but council. You have three
minutes and you're at one minute now.
continue.
>> I go around and I audit things. If the
prosecutor's office, the law director's
office does not like to hear from me
because they lost the battle against me,
that's a problem. If they cannot talk to
the people when the people has an issue,
that becomes the issue that falls on
that person's shoulders in this city.
She gets paid very well.
and I don't want to deep dive like I've
already done a couple other officers to
remove their badges.
So, knowingly, I brought this to you
guys and also the chief of fire
going up that one-way street, busting
those red lights on Harrison,
you guys are allowing that.
Do you know 90 years ago that was
permitted? Very few people lived on that
side of town. And like the chief said,
we did it then. 90 years later, we're
going to continue to do it. Multiple
videos of engine house 2 running that
red light coming up that one leg that
oneway street on Harrison to pull into
the firehouse.
And if the mayor's chief of police would
catch me doing that or catch anybody in
this room, that would be a ticket
pulling into that house if you lived on
that corner.
So, those two issues need to be
resolved. And if the mayor wants to call
me, he has my number. I don't hide.
I don't do that. I won't do that. But if
we're going to replace our law director,
don't don't allow allow her to continue
to represent that office the way she
does.
And I want her and I'm going to under
the law that she protects herself under.
I'm going to do everything in my power.
>> Sir, you've reached your three minute
limit. Thank you and have a good
evening.
>> President Porter, I know we don't
typically respond, but I'd like an
opportunity tonight. Please,
>> I make a motion we go out of the regular
order of business.
>> Okay. So, we have a motion to go out of
the order the regular order of business.
Do we have a second?
Yeah, I'll second that. So, we have a
motion and a second to go out of the
regular order of business. Um, please
call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bizjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg, yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner, yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes. Thank you. We're now outside the
regular order of business and I would
recognize Law Director Hall.
>> Thank you, President Porter. Thank you,
members of council. I just want
everybody to be aware obviously I am law
director and city prosecutor and in my
role as city prosecutor I unfortunately
um have to deal with Mr. Fe on a regular
basis. Um specifically right now the
Fairfield County Sheriff's Department
has forwarded charges to my office uh
requesting charges against Mr. Fe for
stalking one of their deputies while he
does his work um throughout the county.
Uh Mr. fight called and demanded to know
if I was going to issue a warrant for
his arrest. And I told him that that's
not how the process works. We do not
tell criminals who have charges pending
that we are going to issue a warrant for
their arrest and give them a heads up
about that um for the obvious reasons.
So, Mr. Fe is frustrated because uh that
investigation is ongoing. The sheriff's
department is still working to uh
potentially get charges filed against
him. And in the meantime, this is how he
is uh reacting to that situation. So, I
apologize that that this was laid before
all of you. Um but it it should be
resolved here in the near future um to
the satisfaction of of the city and its
residents. I'll just note for the record
too, Mr. Fe is not a city resident. uh
he lives outside of the city limits but
still insists on auditing each and every
one of our police officers, each and
every one of our departments and
agencies. Um and you know, I support the
public records law just as much as
anybody else. But there comes a point um
when it's a waste of everybody's time,
every other taxpayers's time and money
to have to deal with, you know, the one
squeaky wheel. Um and so I, you know,
I'm doing the best I can. Um, and I
can't say everything that I would like
to say, but that's as much as I can
share with you tonight. And I appreciate
your your support and your
consideration. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> There any comment? I There's none, we'll
go back into the regular order of
business and continue with public
comment.
Having none, we're we're back in the
regular order of business. Um, is there
any other individual who wishes to
address city council at this time?
hearing none. We thank you for coming.
Uh reports of standing committees.
>> I have two of them. I have safety
meeting minutes dated December 14th,
2025 submitted by Mr. Bisjek. Finance
committee meeting agenda dated December
15, 2025 submitted by Mr. Skoonover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees.
>> Second. Have a motion, a second to
receive and file the reports of standing
committees. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Reports of
special committees.
>> There are no special reports.
>> Thank you. Public hearings.
>> We have none.
>> We may now move on to the reading of
resolutions. There are no uh third
readings of resolutions this evening.
Second reading. We move to temporary
resolution 105-25.
I have a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to enter into an
agreements with the Fairfield County
Board of Commissioners with various
consultants as needed and to advertise
for bids and enter into a contract for
construction of the project known as the
WY Road Reconstruction Project.
Excuse me. This is through public works
committee. Miss Tener and Mrs. Kates.
>> Council member Tener.
>> Second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 10525.
Temporary resolution 10625,
>> a resolution of consent for preliminary
legislation and to authorize the service
safety director to enter into agreements
as necessary to complete the projects
known as FAI US22
um I'm assuming
and 37 and 158 V um PID 980 01 or 22 and
D05 for year 2027. Bridge Rehab West PID
124808.
This is through public works committee.
Miss Tiner and Mrs. Christ.
>> Council member Tiner.
>> Second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 10625.
We now move on to the first reading of
resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution 11325.
A resolution to approve a then announced
certificate for the payment of the bill
in the general fund 10001 through this
is through code enforcement and zoning
committee. Mr. Sully and Mr. Luckenberg.
>> Council member Sully.
>> Thank you m Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules and wave the second and third
reading of resolution temporarily
numbered 113-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
suspend the rules and we have the second
and third reading of temporary
resolution 11325.
Council member Sully, any discussion on
the motion to suspend?
>> No discussion.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Pische,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lenbury,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Scoover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Teener, yes. And Mr. Wing,
>> yes. Motion to suspend the rules and
wade the second and third reading of
temporary resolution 11325
passes 10 to zero. Council member Sley.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like to
make a motion that C council pass and
engross and error upon the written
record resolution temporarily numbered
113-25.
Second.
>> We have a motion and second to pass and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 11325.
Any discussion?
>> No. Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes. Mr. Carr, yes. Mrs.
Kra, yes. Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luxterberg,
>> Mr. Scoover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sullies,
>> Miss Tiner, yes. And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
11325 passes 10 to zero.
We'll now move on to the reading of
ordinances. We have no third readings
this evening. So we will move to the
second reading of ordinances beginning
with temporary ordinance 7225.
An ordinance determining to to proceed
with the acquisition, construction, and
improvement of certain public
improvements in the city of Lancaster,
Ohio in cooperation with the Lancaster
Regional Energy Special Improvement
District in declaring emergency. This is
through economic development committee,
Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Kra. Council member
Hoop.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules and wave the third reading of
temporary ordinance 72-25.
Second.
>> So, we have a motion in a second to
suspend the rules and wave the uh third
reading of temporary ordinance 7225.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> No.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> Mr. Skover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sie,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
7225 passes 10 to zero. Council member
Hoop.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like to
make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Temporary
ordinance 72-25.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion, a second to pass, gross,
and enter upon the written record.
Temporary ordinance 7225. Any
discussion? and council member Hoop.
>> Um, this is just to proceed with the EID
and the PACE financing that we discussed
the last council meeting.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjag,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. or Mr. Carr, sorry.
>> Mrs. Craig,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Teener, yes. And Mr. Wing,
>> yes. Motion to pass and gross and enter
upon the written record. Temporary
ordinance 7225
passes 10 to zero. We now move to
temporary ordinance 7325.
an ordinance levying special assessments
for the purpose of acquiring,
constructing, and improving certain
public improvements in the city of
Lancaster, Ohio, in cooperation with the
Lancaster Energy Special Improvement
District approving the CPACE assignment
agreement in declaring emergency. This
through economic development committee,
Mrs. Hoop and Mr. Wing.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. And I'd like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules and wave the third reading of
temporary ordinance 73-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to suspend
the rules and wave the third reading of
temporary ordinance 7325.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> No.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mr. Carr, yes.
>> Mrs. Kra, yes. Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover, yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner, yes. And Mr. Wing,
>> yes. Motion to suspend the rules and
wave the third reading of temporary
ordinance 7325
passes 10 to zero. Council member Hoop.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like to
make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Temporary ordinance 73-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
pass gross and enter upon the written
record temporary ordinance 7325.
Any discussion? Council member Hoop.
>> Um, this is along with the PACE
financing. Mr. Setups sets up the
payments um for the Wilson building.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bischek, yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kes,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Locker,
>> Mr. Skover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Ter, yes. And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary ordinance
7325 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
Ordinance 7425,
>> an ordinance to re repeal and replace
Lancaster codified ordinance part one,
administrative code, title 3,
legislative chapter 111,
rules of council and to declare an
emergency. This is through law
committee, Mrs. Kates and Mr. Bisch.
>> Council member Kitz.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like
to make a motion to replace ordinance
temporar temporarily numbered 74-25 by
replacing it with ordinance temporarily
numbered 74-25
star as given to the clerk in writing
prior to tonight's meeting.
>> Second. We have a motion, a second to
pack uh to um replace temporary
ordinance 7425
with temporary ordinance 7425
star which was presented to the clerk in
writing before tonight's meeting. Any
discussion, Council Member Kits?
>> Uh nothing beyond what we've discussed
in finance.
>> Thank you.
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kitz,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Mr. Lockenberg.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Skover.
>> Mr. SI.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> And Mr. Wing.
>> No.
>> Motion to replace uh temporary ordinance
uh with temporary ordinance 7425 star
passes 9 to zero. Council member K.
>> 9 to one.
>> 9 to1. Excuse me. Sorry.
>> Uh Mr. President, I would like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the third reading of ordinance
temporarily numbered 74-25 star.
>> Second motion is and a second to suspend
the rules and wave the third reading of
temporary ordinance 7425 star. Any
discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> Nothing additional.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> no.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Kates.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> No.
>> Mr. Lockenberg.
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sully?
>> Miss Tiner?
>> No.
>> And Mr. Wing?
>> Yes.
>> What is that?
>> One, two, three, fours.
>> Four nos. Okay.
>> Okay. So motion to suspend the rules and
wave the third reading of temporary
ordinance 7425
passes 6 to4
is that Nope. We can't.
>> No, it it fails to pass because you have
to have a super majority in order to
>> I figured that was something. Thank you.
>> All right. So that means that temporary
ordinance 7425 star passes or we we did
we're done. Correct. Yes, it's failed.
>> Okay, it's failed. All right, thank you.
And now we'll move on to the first
reading of ordinances beginning with
temporary ordinance 7525,
>> an ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance 63-25,
the management pay ordinance and to
declare an emergency. This is through
finance committee, Mr. Skunover and Mr.
Als.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the second and third readings of
temporary ordinance 7525.
>> Second.
>> Motion a second to suspend the rules and
wave the second and third reading of
temporary ordinance 7525. Any
discussion? Council members.
>> This is just to fix
an error that that we missed uh on the
previous passage of this pay ordinance
in 6325.
>> Thank you.
Please call the role on the motion to
suspend.
Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kitz,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luxenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Motion to suspend the rules and we have
the second and third reading of
temporary ordinance 7525. Passes 10 to
zero. Council member Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to pass that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 7525.
>> Second motion in the second to pass
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary ordinance 7525.
Any further discussion?
>> No thanks.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes. Miss Tiner.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wing.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary ordinance
7525 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
ordinance 7625.
>> An ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance 64-25
the non-UN pay ordinance and to declare
an emergency. This is through finance
committee. Mr. Skunover, Mr. Als.
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Mr. Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third readings
of temporary ordinance 7625.
>> Second motion and second to suspend the
rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary ordinance 7625.
Any discussion, Council Member Skinner?
>> No. Thanks.
>> Please call the RO.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mr. K. Mrs. Kit, sorry.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luggenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes. Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tinder,
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
ordinance 7625 passes 10 to zero.
Council member Skunover.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 7625.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record. Temporary ordinance
7625.
Any further discussion?
>> No thanks.
Last one of the year.
>> Um,
>> please call the RO.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lecterberg,
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes. And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary ordinance
7625 passes 10 to zero.
That concludes our reading of
legislation uh for this evening. Uh we
do not have any tabled legislation.
Um
unfinished business. We do not have any.
Um we do have a couple of appointments
this evening that I would ask council to
vote on and I would turn it over at this
time to um to the mayor to discuss those
appointments. First, do you want to
discuss the port authority and then the
eid?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. President. Uh, I am requesting the
council um confirm the appointments of
Dean D. Rolf and Natalie Burns to the
Langster Port Authority. Both
>> both of them are longtime members,
longtime members of the Port Authority,
and they bring extensive knowledge of
the Port Authority's mission, what
they've done in the past, and what they
plan to do in the future. So, I'm
recommending they both be reappointed.
Again, Natalie Furnus and Dean D. Rolf.
And you should have received in your
email uh their bios.
>> Thank you.
Can I have a motion to um accept those
appointments to the port authority?
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from let let the record
reflect that council member Tiner made
the motion to um accept those two
appointments.
>> I second, Mr. President. And we have a
second from council member Bisjack. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Thank you.
Uh, now we also have an appointment to
well, two appointments to the energy
sid.
>> Yeah, Mr. President, the um EID, the
energy special improvement district
requires a legislative appointment and a
administrative appointment. for my
administrative appointment. I would like
to recommend the council approve
Stephanie Bosow as our representative to
the EID.
>> Okay. Can I have a motion uh for the
appointment uh for the acceptance of
that appointment?
>> I'll make that.
>> Uh Council Member Luckenberg,
>> I'll second, Mr.
>> And then Mr. Council Member Bisjack
seconds. All those in favor of that
appointment, please signify by saying I.
I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
>> Okay. In the legislative appointment, is
it necessary to do the legislative
appointment this evening or can we do
that at our beginning meeting?
>> Sorry. No, we've got to do it this
evening because they meet tomorrow and
they need the full complement of
committee member or board members there.
>> Okay. Yeah, we just we found out about
that this evening. So, we really haven't
had any opportunity to consider that. I
know there's a discussion that uh
council member Hoop was a person that
might be wanting to do that. We haven't
even had the opportunity. Would you like
to serve in that role?
>> I already spoke with Stephanie Bosco,
but that's fine.
>> Okay. All right. Thank you. Can we have
a motion to appoint uh Council Member
Hoop to that position?
>> So moved.
>> All right. Council member Bisjack.
Second from Council Member Sie. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I. I.
>> Thank you. in the future if we could I
know we just passed legislation tonight
but if we could have that a little bit
earlier we would appreciate it so we
could talk to the folks about it. All
right. Thank you. Um now we've reached
the time in the meeting for additional
new business. We typically ask our
council members uh at this time to give
committee updates but we are going to go
to each person tonight recognizing that
this is um a final meeting for some
folks. But before we do get to that,
we've got a couple of quick recognitions
because some folks aren't going to be
able to make our um meeting well our
swearing in next week. So, at this time,
I'd like a to ask council member uh
former council member Wolfinger to come
forward. We just wanted like to
recognize your service uh to Lancaster
City Council. So if you come forward
>> over there
>> just over over here up here
>> right in the middle
>> around me away from the mic.
>> I just can't jump over.
>> Yeah, exactly.
So,
we'd like to present to you this plaque
in honor of your service as a council
member at large from January 1st, 2024
to June 30th of 2025 and your uh service
as finance chair as well. So, we thank
you for your service. We know you served
as treasurer uh and served in the city
much longer than just your council
service, but we would like to thank you
for your council service this evening.
Thank you very much.
[Applause]
>> And we also have another individual who
um can't make it next week due to work
um which we all have work. Um but
Council Member Tener, please come
forward.
So
Becky, um I would just like to recognize
your council service from January 1st of
uh to December 31st, which is obviously
a few more days from now of 2025. We
truly be thank you for your service. So
thank you.
OF
[Applause]
COURSE, you know, I'm not going to leave
without saying something. So, and I
thought I was going to be the most
exciting thing tonight, but apparently
not.
>> Well, you can go back to your seat and
say it from there.
>> Oh, no. We can do it.
>> Go on.
>> Why at the seat?
>> Because we're going to go in order.
>> We'll get to it.
Okay. All right. Council member Hoop,
any updates?
>> None.
>> Thank you, Council Member Wing.
>> I have a few prepared remarks since it's
my last meeting.
>> Okay.
>> Would you like me to give those now or?
>> Sure. We're going to go in order.
>> Okay. In the room.
>> Give me just a minute. Okay. Well, thank
you all. Um, we navigated through a lot
of tough issues this term and I could
not have asked for a more dedicated and
professional group to work with. I
learned something from each and every
single one of you.
As you all know, this job is much more
than just showing up, voting yes, and
even paying a few pennies into a pension
system.
This term we transferred our transit
department to the county to better serve
our workforce and we saw the completion
of the new transfer station at
sanitation phase two of the upper
hawking uh water pollution control
expansion and the oper and the opening
of the brand new north water plant.
I'd also like to thank all the
department superintendent who met with
me and gave me a tour of all of our city
facilities. I am still to this day in
awe about how well our city operates and
how everything and everyone has to work
together every single day to make it
happen.
Although my time here was short, I can
assure you um the time that was shared
with me was well spent and it was a very
meaningful investment.
I would also like to give a big uh thank
you to the departments overseen by my
committee. Uh these past two years I
learned way more about water treatment
uh wastewater treatment, storm water
mitigation, and environmental
engineering uh than I ever could have
imagined.
I truly enjoyed working with these
departments. We really were the best
committee, the best out of nine.
And uh special thanks to Darren Drum,
Curtis Wii, uh Mike Nixon, Steven
Welstead, and Denise Cruz. Um they
really are the best at what they do. I
would even put them up up against their
counterparts in any other municipality,
and I'm confident ours would be far
superior.
As most of you know, I have lived here
my entire life and found myself coming
to these meetings about four years ago.
Several months after that, I was
approached for the first time to run for
council. And a big thank you to everyone
who's helped me along the way.
I I did want to make a few comments as
to where we are right now. Uh we are
here today in in this situation because
there are some great divisions in our
society uh that have made their way into
our local elections.
Everyone here knows the event that took
place last year that started all of
this. I was chastised for not stopping
it. But I understand from our legal
counsel it is protected by the first
amendment to our to our United States
Constitution.
And I also understand from civics's
class that the Constitution protects
everyone, not just with whom you agree.
Unfortunately, this event was exploited
by a small fringe group to appeal to
people's worst fears and emotions, and
they used the energy from that anger to
get elected. Instead of uniting the city
to find common good, they divided the
city for their own personal and
political benefit.
In order to accomplish this, the group
um and their surrogates uh resorted to
lies and personal attacks such as
calling me a pedophile, going after my
weight, and blatantly lying about what
council can do in the shape of our
city's finances.
I was also called a Columbus insider,
ironically, from a candidate not from
Lancaster, uh who has worked there far
longer than I have. However, I refused
to get involved in the mudslinging
because that is not who we are as a
city.
Although we are divided in times like
these, I'm reminded of our 16th and uh
40th presidents, Abraham Lincoln and
Ronald Reagan, who called on public who
called on all public servants to seek
unity and pursue better angels rather
than divi rather than to divide and seek
our worst fears. Thank you all.
>> Thank you. Thank you for your service,
Council Member.
Council member Carr,
>> probably too new to have much to say
now. Um, just one one comment to uh Mr.
Wing. You got a lot of life in front of
you. Don't make this the last time you
run for public office.
>> Thank you,
>> Council Member Skunover.
>> Um, excuse me.
Uh
trying to think how I want to say this,
but um
>> you know these last two years um you
know we had a bunch of fresh faces, a
bunch of you know I think in every term
we there's always a hot button issue.
There's always a lot to do. I think uh
everyone has handled themselves with
grace as far as that goes. I've I've sat
up here multiple times and talked about
the art of neighboring. And I think
the neighboring part really just it it
intensifies when you sit up here. You
know, we had a public hearing not too
long ago where we had someone ask like,
"Hey, do you really listen to what we
have to say when we come up here?" And,
you know, my answer was we do. I mean,
we it's it's a struggle for some of the
decisions that we make and then we put a
lot of time and effort into it that
maybe not be seen. Um, and we've been
through the the trenches together. So
whether you're coming, going, staying,
you know, that's important to me. Um,
we're always going to be friends in some
way, shape, or form. Uh, because we've
been through it together. Um, so I
appreciate everyone around around the
room and I'm hoping that um as we
continue the journey in in Lancaster
that, you know, we figure it out and we
keep doing the art of neighboring. And
if you haven't figured out the art of
neighboring, you know, read up on it and
if you have questions, I can help you
with that. That's all I got. Thank you,
council member team.
>> Okay. First of all, I'd like to uh there
there's two couples that always watch
and I'm going to call them out. Uh Kathy
and Ed Snyder and Alton and Bonnie Currs
on Moving Road. They never miss our
meetings ever. So, I just kind of wanted
to shout out to them. Um first of all,
I'd like to thank the citizens of the
six ward for allowing me to serve you
these past 12 years. You have become
friends and very much family. Also, Dr.
Reichman, Janet Moralt, Tim Welker,
Duard Watts, Bob Hedges, and the late
Randy Grath who encouraged me to run. It
took a huge effort from all three
parties to get me elected in the general
election in 2013. Many people helped
behind the scenes. Also the Crooks,
Mandavvilles, Keners, Sheets, Lines,
Currences, Burgesses, Linda Morgan,
Kevin and Mary Groves, Debbie Longshore,
Sherry Waters, the Smurs, Maggie Brown,
and countless others that helped me keep
track of our neighborhoods. There isn't
anything I could have done without them.
I'm very proud of our safety forces. Oh,
and I forgot to mention family. If I
don't mention family, I'll really be in
trouble. Sorry about that. We always
leave them out. I'm very proud of our
safety forces. I think that Chief Snyder
has absolutely made our police
department much better. Chief Schultz is
working very diligently to get our
muchneeded firehouse built. However, the
heroes of our city aren't the
administration, city council, or the
safety forces. The city couldn't run
without the endless workings of our
street, sanitation, water, gas, IT, and
parks. They are the very reason the city
can function. Also, I want to thank Mary
and Mike Tussy, Tom Stoton, Mayor
McDaniel, Mary Groves, and countless
others for helping me with my campaign.
I'm not going anywhere, so anyone at any
time can call me if I can do anything to
address the election in May. I wasn't
reelection reelected, as you know.
However, I came from a pretty good
bloodline of tough people.
My six uncles and dad were all in World
War II. I would sit and listen to their
stories. One of my uncles in the Navy
was in World War II, Korea and Vietnam.
He also received the Purple Heart. In
1982, at the age of 19, I entered the
medical field. At the time, I it was the
beginning of the AIDS crisis. So, for
several years, I was in the middle of an
epidemic. Then in 2004, I started
working on a children's cancer floor,
which I'm still working there for almost
22 years now.
So to not win an election is absolutely
not the worst thing that could happen to
someone. As we were walking out of our
last council meeting the last night
before the election, Councilman Als
said, "Wednesday, you'll either be happy
or relieved."
And those were the very words that would
have come out of my dad's mouth. to
right then I know I'd be fine.
However, the part of the election that
isn't fine
were the lies and innuendos told not
just about me but others as well. I had
taken a picture after a council meeting
one night
with Mayor McDaniel and Tom Stoton who
endorsed me for city council. Within
minutes after my posting, my opponent
took my picture and reposted it and
typed, "Sad to see that the
establishment will always protect the
status quo. 10 plus years of raising
your taxes, letting the sidewalks
crumble, and letting drag shows happen
in front of our kids." For the record,
on my factchecking, none of these
candidates in what I have called the
Amish Mafia SLSwives
group never went to our mayor, safety
director, or any departments to find out
how this city works. They never came to
any of my committee meetings or any
other committee meetings to my
knowledge. City council did not raise
taxes. The voters voted for the
increase. As for letting sidewalks
crumble, that is the responsibility of
the home or business owners. However, I
have always said if a sidewalk is
damaged because of a city tree, the city
should be responsible. We also have a
sidewalk program. The two streets that
are Hubert and Ree will finally be
paved, which neither Nisley or OG had
anything to do with. That's for the
record in case they bring it up that it
was one it was done because of them. And
as for the drag shows, I never let that
happen or endorsed it. I even made my
feelings clear. I couldn't do anything
to stop it, nor could the police that
night. So during this election, either
they knew the truth and lied or they
don't know how to they don't know how to
fact check. Nisely even made a statement
that crime is increasing, which I
actually have on my phone in one of his
comments on Facebook. He needs to go and
check the stats on the city's website.
And for the record, I never took an
increase in salary the entire 12 years
on council. Also, many of the people in
this group don't even live in Lancaster.
They apparently found individuals with a
pulse that would run. The group that
calls themselves Christians even after
min the group that calls themselves
Christians even went after ministers and
churches. But one thing that happened
from that night and is still happening.
Shortly after the downtown shows, 16
ministers met to help and pray over our
community. They are still meeting and
planning events today. Last December,
they held a candlelight service in the
downtown with several ministers reading
the Christmas story with several
attending. Even though the drag show
wasn't good, the I'm sorry. The weather
wasn't good, not the drag show. Sorry
about that. I don't know. It says
weather, not drag.
However, I never saw any of these people
calling themselves Christians the night
of the drag show. I was told that it was
because the ministers reached out to
Provisions in El City for cookies and
hot chocolate. I ate a cookie and drank
hot chocolate. Over a year later, I'm
still straight.
I'm a Christian. However, I'm a work in
progress. Every day I do I say or do
something that I think that I shouldn't.
I'm sorry. Every day I say, do or think
something that I shouldn't. I even have
a glass at home that says I believe in
Jesus, but I cuss a little. I'm not
perfect and will never be perfect. But I
sure know God's grace. My brothers and I
were brought up not to hate or dislike
anyone. However, you might not like what
they do. I have friends and family of
all backgrounds, beliefs, lifestyles,
etc. Some people call themselves
Christians. Some people that call
themselves Christians are actually the
worst advertisement for Christianity.
From the ministers I talked to and with
my Bible reading, sin isn't rated. Sin
is sin. So remember, lying and deception
is sin. I always made my feelings known
on council floor be about public
bathrooms. I even met with several
people from the alliance group. We had
very healthy conver discussions and both
sides agreed to disagree. I never one
time saw anything by them on social
media about me. But I can't say that
about the Amish Mafia sister wife group.
During the campaign, Mike Tussy made
posts supporting my election. Frank
Clark stated on that post, "The single
women goes far with most men. I don't
even know what that means." However, he
was arrested this past summer for an
incident and actually called me right
after he got out of jail, it appeared,
and left me a message to call him. So,
not only can this group wave red, white,
and blue, they can also add orange, and
white to their colors because that's the
color of the Fairfield County Jail.
So, in closing, it's okay to have debate
and disagreement, but it's it's how you
disagree can be the problem. Vote the
right way and not what you're
comfortable with. be brave enough to do
what's right even when others don't.
>> Thank you, Council Member Tiner.
>> Council member Kates.
>> Um, I did not actually prepare anything
because I didn't really realize this was
my last meeting until I got here. So, I
would just say that I have learned a
lot. I really appreciate all of the help
along the way, not only with the current
council members, but the prior council
that was here before as well. Um, I have
a much better appreciation for all of
the city um, administration and the
workers and the process um, because it's
a lot different than what I thought it
was before actually joining council. And
I'm very excited to see where this city
goes in the future with the new council
and where you guys take us.
>> That's it.
>> Thank you, Council Member Kates. Council
member Als,
>> I have nothing. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Council Member Luckenberg. I
have no committee update, but I do have
some parting remarks. Uh, I'd just like
to say it's been a pleasure getting to
know all of you around this table. It's
been a a real joy getting to know you
all this year. It's been my honor to
serve the citizens of Lancaster and to
serve alongside of all of you. It truly
has been an honor. I consider you not
only as fellow council men and women,
but also as friends.
I hope you feel the same.
Uh, I'd like to thank Christina Christ
for coaching me when I was first
appointed. What a blessing you were.
She was council clerk back then. And I'd
like to thank you all who helped me
along the way as well. I'd like to thank
my wife Debbie for putting up with me.
I had a pretty pretty heaped up plate
for a while between this and my office
and our church. So, but it's been a joy
and I'd like to publicly give praise to
Mayor Don McDaniels,
to service safety director Carrie Woody.
Where where is she tonight?
>> Christmas shopping with her.
>> Oh,
she has her priorities.
to law director Stephanie Hall, to city
auditor Trisha Nettles, and to city
treasurer Tom Stoton. You guys work
tirelessly for this city, and I want the
citizens to know how good our leadership
is here. It's amazing how many countless
things you guys oversee, the many hats
you all wear, and the grace that you
carry your duties out with. It's it's
truly amazing. I'd like to thank Jeff
Porter, our city council president.
You're on a tight ship here and I
appreciate that. You've done a fine job.
The thing that just blew me away uh in
addition to all of you
uh is the hundreds of folks in the
various city departments behind the
scenes folks. I met many of them in my
council meetings. They are the unsung
heroes. They don't get the praise. They
don't get the limelight that we all get.
And yet without them, this city wouldn't
operate. They do a magnificent job. And
uh I want the city to know this. It's
been an eye-opening experience for me
and a huge blessing to be in this seat
for the past two years. And Amy Cohen, I
congratulate you on winning the election
and I wish you the best. I'll be praying
for you and I I pray that you'll handle
this position with the honor and we'll
give it the TLC that the citizens of
Lancaster deserve. Congrats.
That's all I have.
>> Thank you, Council Member Bisjack.
>> I have nothing.
>> Thank you, Council Member Sie. I I don't
have a committee update, but I I will
say it was a year ago that I was
appointed to this council, and I really
uh appreciate everybody's help here. I
think almost about everybody around this
table has stepped up to help me and get
me on board and up to speed quickly. And
I'm I'm really grateful. And I will tell
you that when I I came into this role,
you know, I told myself either I'm going
to find out how things really work in
this city and either going to be scared
to death
or, you know, I'm going to be happy with
what I see. And I got to tell you what
I've learned in the last year is I'm
very proud of this city, the the folks
that work for our city, our city
leadership, this council, and the
citizens of this town. I I couldn't be
more proud of the place I live. And you
know, I've lived in Lancaster for
probably 32 years now and um I'm really
proud to call it home. We have a lot to
be proud of and we've got great things
ahead of us. That's all I have. Thank
you. We do have some additional new
business this evening. Um a couple of
liquor permits that we've received.
>> We have um a couple we have four of
them. As a matter of fact, we have two
transfers and two new ones. We have the
G or J A Lancaster LLC. Um, onetop carry
out transferring from 803 onetop carry
out LLC. Um, and then 1649 East Main
Street, Lancaster, transferring from
VHVLP
LLC estate. Those
>> Let's do the transfers first.
>> Okay. Um, so we have two liquor
transfers that have now been read. Um, I
take it we just need to approve those
transfers or not object to those
transfers.
>> Correct.
>> Correct. Okay. Thank you. Um, I take a
motion to approve the transfers unless
anybody has a a hard reason to object.
>> Move to approve, Mr. President.
>> We got a we got a motion to approve and
a second uh from um motion to approve
from council member Bisjack. Second from
council member Tiner. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Thank you.
Now, we'll go to the new permit
applications.
>> Have two new ones. Um, Family Ties Diner
LLC and Los Maras.
>> Maras.
>> Looks like Los Mariachis.
>> Oh jeez. Yeah. This is why I read for a
living. It's why I like numbers. um Boss
Mariachi of Lancaster. I was told um by
Lieutenant Underwood that this one is
actually where FRE's is going to be.
>> Um there was no
no bad background of that one. Um and
then as for the family ties dinner, they
looked up that address and they didn't
have anything bad come from that one
either.
>> Okay. So we would either take a motion
to approve or object. Uh do we have a
motion to approve? I move, Mr.
President.
>> Council member Bisjack, second from uh
Council Member Tiner, uh to approve
those two new permits. All those in
favor, please signify by saying, "I."
>> Those opposed, same sign.
>> Thank you. We'll now move on to the uh
with no additional new business this
evening, the announcement of scheduled
meetings.
>> I have next regular sessions of council
January 12th, 2026 at 6:30 p.m. here in
council chambers. And then again January
26th, 2026 at 6:30 p.m. here in CH
council chambers.
>> Special scheduled meeting.
>> I have one January 5th um 2026 at 6:00
p.m. at city hall 1897 conference room
>> and that is the council reorganization
meeting. So all um council members
should make plans to attend that
meeting.
Um we have no regularly scheduled
committee meetings at this time. We now
move on to the reading of bills.
>> I do have um three of them, but one I
have not received the invoice, but I
wanted to let you know what it's going
to be before um I ordered legislation
books to put all of my um legislation
ordinances, resolutions, and minutes
through. and I need those every year um
in order to keep those organized and
file away in the safe. Um I have not
received that invoice yet. So once that
comes through that'll be on my agenda
again to let you know how much it was.
Um the spotlight awards um $296 for
plaques name is and name plates for
councils and then um MNCO $26.32
for publication of ordinances um
permanent ordinance 7025 and permanent
order 7020 7125.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to pay the bills.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to pay the
bills. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. All those posed, same sign. We have
no need for an executive session this
evening. Um I now I will take a motion
to adjourn our final meeting of this
term.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make that
motion we adjourn.
>> Second.
>> A motion and second to adjurnn. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
>> No.
>> Okay, there you go. Oh, wow.
>> All right. Final word.
>> Before we uh before we adjourn, can we
get a picture out here? Yeah, before
>> before everybody all council members um
and administration leave for this
evening, we'd like to get everybody
together to take a photo up here. So, um
if you could uh make yourself available
and please remember to sign your
legislation before you leave this
evening.
>> Let's do the picture before we do all
that.
[Music]